A Guide to the War of 1812 Collection, 1806-1823
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
War of 1812 Collection, 1806-1823
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2017-013
0.3 Cubic Feet 1 box
This collection contains correspondence and military documents relating to the War of 1812, including materials before, during, and after the war, with a particular emphasis on activities in Virginia between 1806 and 1823.
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The War of 1812 Collection was purchased in multiple accession by Special Collections during 2017. Additinoal materials may be added in the future.
Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence and military documents relating to the War of 1812, including materials before, during, and after the war, with a particular emphasis on activities in Virginia between 1806 and 1823. The bulk of the collection consists of letters written by individuals involved with or talking about the conflict. In addition, there are a small number of military documents, including battalion and regimental court marshalls, court summons, and printed materials from 1807-1817.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series. Series I: Letters, 1806-1823, contains letters by civilians and members of the military before the outbreak of the War of 1812, during the war, and in the immediate and extended aftermath. This series is in chronological order. Series II: Military Documents and Printed Materials, 1807-1817, includes battalion and regimental court marshalls from the 1st and 2nd Virginia Militia, a court summons, and a publication. this series is in chronological order.
Index Terms
Subjects:
United States -- History -- War of 1812
Contents List
- Series I: Letters, 1806-1823
  - Benjamin Turner, 1806-09-20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Letter from Benjamin Turner to Henry Ward Esq., written on September 20, 1806. This letter discusses Turner's sailing to New Orleans along with news of a withdrawal of funds and his request that Ward enclose money in another letter to Mr. Ben Bourne, from whom Turner borrowed $50.
  - Dennis Smelt, 1808-03-23 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Letter from Dennis Smelt to William Pollard Esq., written on March 23 1808. The subject of the letter includes informaiton on political acquaintance affairs and social events.
  - James Pratt, 1810-07-07 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Letter from James Pratt to Henry Ward Esq., written on July 7, 1810. The letter details information including Pratt's safe arrival after traveling from New York, along with advice for how to live happily as one progresses through life.
  - William Hazard, 1810-11-05 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Letter from William Hazard to Henry Ward Esq., written on November 5, 1810. The letter includes information about Hazard receiving goods from England and shipping informaiton, along with Hazard's wishes to be in France when the British shipping orders are carried out.
  - G Hagdorn, 1812-03-05 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Letter from G. Hagdorn to John G Wachsmuth, written on March 5, 1812. Hagdorn's letter details his travel information to England and the great differences between America and London, where Hagdorn had recently moved. In addition to the description of the differences between the two areas, Hagdorn writes, encouraging Wachsmuth to leave Philadelphia and come to London.
  - Samuel Jordan Harrison, 1812-07-07 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Letter from Samuel Jordan Harrison to his brother, Jordan Harrison, written on July 7, 1812. Harrison writes to his brother, regarding Indian hostilities and activity in the new state of Ohio and his wishes for their family not to travel to the area until later, as a way of avoiding these dangerous areas and activities.
  - Thomas Colman Searle, 1812-09-19 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Letter from Thomas Colman Searle to his sister, Nancy Searle, written on September 19, 1812. Searle's letter to his sister includes information about home family life along with a separate note to his parents, and discusses family and acquaintance news. Searle's letter also details his account of attending a trial of a woman named Sarah, and her potential death and last words: "when she was brought to the trial, she displayed the most surprising resignation to death"
  - James Clements, 1812-11-07 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Letter from James Clements to Reuben Haines Esq., written on November 7, 1812. This letter details acquaintance news of traveling and shipping goods, along with a discussion of personal accounts.
  - John Heiner, 1813-05-22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Letter from John Heiner to Samuel Johnson Esq., written on May 22, 1813, detailing his safe arrival after travel and the fact that he found his family safe upon arrival, "we are all well here and wish to be remembered by all"
  - Timothy Paxson, 1813-06-17 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Letter from Timothy Paxson to Moses Eastburn, written on June 17, 1813. Paxson's letter details information on a settlement of a debt, and news of issues with making sales: "our port is now closely blockaided and during its continuance we do not expect to be able to make sales of any kind of produce."
  - D.L. Greene, 1813-08-16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Letter from D.L. Greene, written on August 16, 1813. This letter contains news of having procured letters to go to Washington in order to get a warrant in the navy, and acquaintance/colleague news. Archibald Kearny to Henry Ward Esq.
  - Sarah Harriet Young, 1814-07-03 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Letter from Sarah Harriet Young to her sister, Mrs. Joseph Nourse, written on July 3, 1814. Young's letter details news of family and friend acquaintances, a request for new black silk/sable fabric for a dress, and additionally Young jokes about a nickname for her sister.
  - William King, 1814-09-11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Letter from William King to Lieutenant Colonel Jacob Ulmer, written on September 11, 1814. King's letter details military movements and the denial of request to send troops: "which renders it necessary for me to order first Coln Cummings back to this Division believing that you will be able to do every thing which is necessecary while acting on the defensive."
  - Philip Duval, 1815-05-24 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Letter from Philip Duval to Miss Caleb Taylor and C. E. Smith, written on May 24, 1815. Duval worked as a druggist and this letter is written as a request for specific items that need to be carried on the ship "Minerva", including a list containing: crude white arsenic, epson salts, vials, rochelle salts and yellow bark powder.
  - Henry Hubbard, 1816-05-23 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Letter from Henry Hubbard to Henry Ward, written on May 23, 1816. Hubbard's letter discusses finances, notes, treasury notes, bills from London. He states that he is not quite ready to give certain other notes, but hopes to be [ready] soon.
  - James T.B. Romayne, 1816-11-07 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Letter from James T.B. Romayne to Col. Thomas Aspinwall, written on November 7, 1816. The letter expresses Romayne's disappointment in the attempt to court martail General Edmund Pendleton Gaines, for Gaines was considered a hero for actions taken at Sackets Harbor and at the Battle of Fort Erie.
  - Joseph Allen, 1818-07-04 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Letter from Captain Joseph Allen to Major William Crawford, written on July 27, 1818. Allen's letter details sending a brigade order in request for Crawford's attendance at a court martial and details the names of the soliders that will be sent to accompany Crawford on the journey to court: "Your companions will be Lt. Col Mr Lincoln, Lt Col. Damon, Major Holmes + Fisk and three Capt from 5th Reg."
  - Rob. Abbott and Company, 1821-07-14 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Letter from business based in Richmond, Rob Abbott and Company to customer, Edward A. Russell, written on July 14. 1821. Abbott and Company's letter is a dicussion of shipment of goods and items to sale.
  - John C. Vowell, 1822-01-01 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Letter from John C. Vowell to William Young, written on January 1, 1822. Vowell's letter is a thank you note for recieval of a check for $20,000 and discusses the fact that a lawyer will send a second check for the like amount, and a request to keep an account of postage, which Vowell will pay for later.
  - James Hagarty, 1822-08-31 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Letter from James Hagarty to Thomas Butler Esq., written on August 31, 1822. Hagarty's letter includes a congratulations on Butler's arrival in England and extends his best wishes to the rest of the family. Additionally, Hagarty's letter includes a detailed account kept for Butler that details purchases and money exhchanges: "a presence of business today will not permit me to say more than merely that your account is enclosed in compliance with your request and that you may remit the balance or pay it over to our Mr. Curven[?] in Philadelphia."
  - W.H. Sumner, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Letter from General W.H. Sumner to Hon. William H Crawford, written in 1823. Sumner's letter regards a dispute over a land purchase and the proposed building of a road. Sent privately by courier with envelope (enclosed).
- Series II: Military Documents and Publications, 1807-1817
  - Battalion Court Martial, 1st Virginia Militia, September 9, 1807, bound with Battalion Court Marshall, 2nd Virginia Militia, October 8, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Publication, "Peace without Dishonour- War without Hope", 1807 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Court Summons for John Hynes, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Battalion Court Marshall, 1st Virginia Militia, October 16, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Regimental Court Marshall, 1st Virginia Militia, October 30, 1815 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Battalion Court Marshall, 1st Virginia Militia, October 18, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Muster Orders and Payment Orders, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 28)